Return to Pandora.
Avatar: The Way of Water is a action, adventure, science
fiction film directed by James Cameron.
Set more than a decade after the events of the first film, learn the story of the Sully family (Jake, Neytiri, and their kids), the trouble that
follows them, the lengths they go to keep each other safe, the battles they fight to stay alive, and the tragedies they endure.
Jake Sully, played by Sam Worthington.
Neytiri, played by Zoe Saldaña.
Kiri, played by Sigourney Weaver.
Colonel Miles Quaritch, played by Stephen Lang.
Ronal, played by Kate Winslet.
Tonowari, played by Cliff Curtis.
Avatar: The Way of Water is a 2022 American epic science fiction film directed by
James Cameron and written by Cameron, Rick Jaffa and Amanda Silver.
It is the second in the Avatar film series.
Sam Worthington, Zoe Saldaña and Stephen Lang reprise their roles from the first film, with
Sigourney Weaver returning in an additional role and Kate Winslet joining the cast.
The plot follows Jake Sully, a human-turned-Na'vi, and
his family on the habitable moon Pandora.
Hunted by RDA forces, they flee to an oceanic region to
seek refuge with the Metkayina clan.
Following the success of Avatar in 2009, two sequels were
announced, with the first aiming for a 2014 release.
However, the addition of two more sequels—for a total of five films—and the need to develop new
technology to film performance capture scenes underwater, led to significant delays.
The filming process, which occurred simultaneously with the third film in the franchise,
Avatar: Fire and Ash, began in Manhattan Beach, California, on August 15, 2017.
Production moved to Wellington, New Zealand the following month, and
was completed three years later, in September 2020.
With an estimated budget of $350–460 million, Avatar: The Way of
Water is one of the most expensive films ever made.
It was produced by Cameron's company Lightstorm Entertainment.
After repeated delays in release, Avatar: The Way of Water premiered at the Odeon Leicester Square theater in London
on December 6, 2022, and was released in the United States on December 16, by 20th Century Studios.
The film received generally positive reviews from critics, who praised the visual
effects and technical achievements but criticized the runtime.
It was a major box office success, breaking multiple records.
It grossed $2.320 billion in its first theatrical run, becoming the
highest-grossing film of 2022 and the third-highest-grossing film of all time.
Among its many accolades, it was named one of the top-ten films of 2022 by
The National Board of Review and the American Film Institute.
It was also nominated for four awards at the 95th Academy Awards,
including Best Picture, and won for Best Visual Effects.
Fire and Ash was released in 2025.
Two additional sequels are scheduled to be
released in 2029 and 2031, respectively.
The film explores themes of dying and death, loss of loved one,
alien life-form, resurrection, dysfunctional family.
The tone is lighthearted and thought_provoking.